<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Assange Court Report</title>
    <description>An archive of daily dispatches, photography and video from the Julian Assange extradition hearings in London, 2020-2024.</description>
    <link>https://assangecourt.report/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://assangecourt.report/it/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 13:45:29 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 13:45:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.1.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Assange Court Report archived</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assange Court Report website archived&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Material on this website remains free for all to use - refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;permissions&quot;&gt;permissions&lt;/a&gt; page for details on licensing and attribution&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early 2020, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blueprintforfreespeech.net&quot;&gt;Blueprint for Free Speech&lt;/a&gt; set up the Assange Court Report as part of our Bridges for Media Freedom project. Our intention was to produce a series of concise and objective daily reports from WikiLeaks Publisher Julian Assange’s extradition hearings - a historically important legal case for freedom of expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our reporting, which settled into twice-daily reports from court and accompanying photographs of the scenes outside, took in the initial extradition hearing in February and September 2020, the first appeal to the High Court in October 2021 and the application for a second appeal in Feburary 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That appeal, which was due to be heard in July 2024, was superseded by the &lt;a href=&quot;assange-freed&quot;&gt;plea deal&lt;/a&gt; that enabled Julian Assange to enter Australia as a free man in June that year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way, we also covered a series of procedural and case management hearings and published many of the &lt;a href=&quot;categories#Documents&quot;&gt;legal documents&lt;/a&gt; from the case. Much of this material has not been well-recorded elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the start of the project, we intended these reports and images to be freely used by others. This remains the case and we hope this archive will prove useful for those who want to understand how the legal arguments in this case proceeded on a day-to-day basis. For licensing and attribution information, please &lt;a href=&quot;permissions&quot;&gt;see here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current dynamics in the media industry have made the economics of regular court reporting challenging. Open justice demands that the public is able to follow events in court, particularly when cases have an impact on issues of genuine public importance. In this case in particular, much of which took place during the Covid-19 epidemic, public access to the courtroom was often extremely difficult to secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope that the Assange Court Report stands as an example of how civil society can step in to remedy gaps in the contemporaneous reporting provided by commercial media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though much of the work on the Court Report was uncredited, at this point we want to acknowledge and thank our key contributors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prime among them was James Doleman, an exemplary reporter and a good friend, who authored all of the reporting on this website through the first set of appeals in 2022. James’ passing in July 2023 was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pressgazette.co.uk/news/james-doleman-dies-tributes/&quot;&gt;great loss to British journalism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later reporting was supplied by Sara Chessa, who has been closely involved in this project from its inception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would also like to thank Guy Smallman, who provided much of the photography featured on this website. Photographs from the initial extradition hearings at Woolwich Magistrates’ Court were taken by Jekaterina Saveljeva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any inquiries about the project can be directed to us at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:contact@bridgesforfreedom.media&quot;&gt;contact@bridgesforfreedom.media&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://assangecourt.report/court-report-archived</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://assangecourt.report/court-report-archived</guid>
        
        
        <category>Reports</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Julian Assange freed from Belmarsh prison after agreeing plea deal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Julian Assange freed from Belmarsh prison after agreeing plea deal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After spending over five years incarcerated in the UK’s high security Belmarsh prison, WikiLeaks Publisher Julian Assange has been freed from the threat of prosecution in the United States. WikiLeaks confirmed that Assange had been released from Belmarsh prison on the morning of on Monday 24 June and boarded a plane out of the UK at 5pm local time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has as yet been no official statement from the US Department of Justice. But, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2024/06/24/us/politics/assange-plea.html&quot;&gt;according to reports&lt;/a&gt;, Assange has agreed to plead guilty to one of the eighteen felony charges he faced, one of conspiring with whistleblower Chelsea Manning to obtain national defence information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Court documents from the US District Court in the Northern Mariana Islands in the Pacific suggest that Julian Assange may make a court appearance there to confirm the plea deal. According to reports, Assange will then return to Australia, a country he has not set foot in since 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of this case and several years of extradition hearings in the UK – which we have been following closely at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blueprintforfreespeech.net/en/news/julian-assange-freed-from-belmarsh-prison-after-agreeing-plea-deal&quot;&gt;Blueprint for Free Speech&lt;/a&gt; – we have repeatedly raised the alarm about what the US prosecution meant for the day-to-day work of investigative journalists working with their sources. Many of those questions about the future of national security journalism in the US and beyond will need to be asked with even greater urgency in the wake of today’s news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is no doubt that Julian Assange’s release from prison will delight the many individuals and organisations who have been working hard for this result for years, both in public and behind the scenes. In addition to our public courtroom coverage, Blueprint launched a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blueprintforfreespeech.net/en/news/blueprint-launches-pardon-campaign-for-assange&quot;&gt;campaign for Julian Assange’s pardon&lt;/a&gt; in 2021. We would like to thank everyone who has been part of our efforts – and everyone else’s – to avoid the catastrophe of a US prosecution of Julian Assange. Today’s news is enormous for Assange and his family, but it also belongs to all of us.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://assangecourt.report/assange-freed</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://assangecourt.report/assange-freed</guid>
        
        
        <category>Reports</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>High Court finds US assurances insufficient and grants permission to appeal against extradition</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Court finds US assurances insufficient and grants permission to appeal against extradition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The High Court decided on Monday to grant WikiLeaks Publisher Julian Assange permission to appeal against his potential extradition to the United States, where he faces an unprecedented set of charges related to WikiLeaks’ publications between 2010 and 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March, the High Court had ruled that Assange would have been granted leave to appeal only if the United States were unable to provide the court with valid assurances on two separate issues: that there was no risk of the death penalty being sought in his case; and that he would be able to  rely on the First Amendment as a legal defence without being discriminated against on the basis of his nationality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Assange did not appear during today’s hearing for health reasons. Edward Fitzgerald KC, for Assange, stated in front of the judges, Victoria Sharp and Jeremy Johnson, that the assurance provided by the US Government on the death penalty was accepted by his client, since it is unambiguous and would be binding for the US courts.  The discussion then turned to the second assurance. “It does not promise that the applicant can rely on the First amendment, it merely saysthat he can raise and seek to rely on it,” Fitzgerald said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fitzgerald argued that a critical absence in the language of the assurance was any obligation on the prosecution not to argue that First Amendment rights should not apply. This was particularly important since the suggestion had originally come from the affidavit of a senior prosecutor for the Eastern District of Virginia, Gordon Kromberg. Furthermore, even if the assurance had contained this language, it was a settled constitutional point in the US that no assurance could bind a federal court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Summers KC, also for Assange, noted that, given the language of the UK Extradition Act, US prosecutors could argue that its non-discriminations provisions did not apply given that “nationality as a concept is somehow narrower than citizenship.” Summers stated that such argument is “plain wrong when one looks at the Refugee Convention… British citizenship is one of many forms of being a national and one can’t be a citizen without being a national.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Lewis KC then rose on behalf of the US Government. He said the law, including European Convention on Human Rights, only protects “responsible journalism.” The US Government held that Assange may not be entitled to First Amendment protections, but this was on the basis of the manner of his publications, rather than his nationality:  “no-one, neither US Citizens nor foreign citizens, are entitled to rely on the First Amendment in relation to publication of illegally obtained  national defence information giving the names of innocent sources to their grave and imminent risk of harm.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Summers responded to the US assertion that citizenship is just one of the factors involved in deciding whether First Amendment rights apply. “The fact remains, and the US accepts it, that non-US citizenship is one of three relevant factors. And it is an important factor in this case.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben Watson, representing the UK Home Secretary, who is also a respondent in this appeal, asked the judges to dismiss the appeal in relation to the role of the then Home Secretary in authorising Julian’s extradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ruling came at the end of the hearing. The judges said the US submissions on non-discrimination were not sufficient and granted the WikiLeaks publisher permission to appeal in relation to the points on freedom of speech and nationality. A full appeal hearing will follow. The parties have been given time until May 24 to submit a proposed outline for how the hearing will proceed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://assangecourt.report/may-20-24-pm</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://assangecourt.report/may-20-24-pm</guid>
        
        
        <category>Reports</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Legal submissions on US assurances</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Below you’ll find submissions from Julian Assange’s legal team on the sufficiency of assurances submitted by the US Government - as well as the US Government response - for the appeal hearing on 20 May 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bridgesforfreedom.media/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/5-240430-Assange-submissions-re-assurance-final-for-filing.pdf&quot;&gt;Assange legal team submission&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bridgesforfreedom.media/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/First-Respondents-Submissions-on-Assurances-14.5.2024.pdf&quot;&gt;US response&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bridgesforfreedom.media/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/10-240516-Reply-final-for-filing.pdf&quot;&gt;Response from Assange legal team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://assangecourt.report/may-20-docs</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://assangecourt.report/may-20-docs</guid>
        
        
        <category>Documents</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Assange Assurances Hearing Photos: May 20, 2024</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Photos from the the Julian Assange assurances hearing at the Royal Courts of Justice in London, May 20, 2024. All photos credit: Guy Smallman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are welcome to reproduce these photos for free as part of the contribution of this archive. Please include a tagline “credit: Guy Smallman”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class=&quot;recent-posts&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;row listrecent&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;

&lt;script&gt;

var gallery_images = [];
var gallery_captions = { 
};
var gallery_credits = {  
};
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;myModal&quot; class=&quot;modal&quot; onclick=&quot;closeModal()&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gclose cursor&quot; onclick=&quot;closeModal()&quot;&gt;&amp;times;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;modal-content&quot; id=&quot;modal_content&quot; onclick=&quot;closeModal()&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;myimg item-fade&quot; onload=&quot;fadeIn()&quot; id=&quot;slideimg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;numbertext&quot; id=&quot;number_div&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; 
        &lt;div class=&quot;caption-container item-fade&quot; id=&quot;caption-container&quot; onclick=&quot;ignoreClick()&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p id=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;  
      
       
      &lt;!-- Next/previous controls --&gt;
      &lt;a class=&quot;gprev&quot; onclick=&quot;plusSlides(event,-1)&quot;&gt;&amp;#10094;&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;a class=&quot;gnext&quot; onclick=&quot;plusSlides(event,1)&quot;&gt;&amp;#10095;&lt;/a&gt;
  
      &lt;!-- Caption text --&gt;
      
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://assangecourt.report/assurances-photos-en/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://assangecourt.report/assurances-photos-en/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Photos</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Assange Court Report: February 21 - afternoon</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of extradition safeguards revealed in final session of Assange hearing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hearing that could mark WikiLeaks Publisher Julian Assange’s final opportunity to oppose his extradition to the United States closed on Wednesday with no announcement of a date for the judges’ decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the afternoon session, the lack of protections Assange would face in the case of extradition became the subject of a series of probing questions from one of the judges who will determine that decision. A lawyer representing the Secretary of State for the Home Department (SSHD) told the court that the latter “has limited powers to prevent extradition in this case”. According to the barrister, consideration of any rights in the Treaty, such as the political offence exception, that are not explicitly incorporated into UK legislation is not at discretion of the SSHD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the issue of potential changes to the charges Assange faces once he is extradited – something that is usually prohibited in extradition cases - Mr Justice Johnson asked the Secretary of State’s representative if there is any safeguard to prevent this happening. The lawyer confirmed that there were not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probing further, Mr Justice Johnson asked if the SSHD’s representative accepted that some charges that might be added in the future could lead to the death penalty. The lawyer said he accepted that risk in principle. Mr Justice Johnson then asked clarifications on whether there was a way to prevent death penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It would be very difficult to offer assurances that prevent death penalty from being imposed,” said the lawyer. However, “This does not mean the Secretary of State was wrong” when she authorised extradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, Mark Summers KC, representing Julian Assange, gave his own response on this issue. “We don’t understand why there is no usual death penalty assurances in this case,” he said. The consequence, Summers argued, is that  - given the UK’s opposition to the death penalty - discharge of the extradition “must follow” if the US refuses to give such assurances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joel Smith KC, for the Government of the United States, told the judges that “imposing UK sentencing policy” on the United States is not part of the function of the UK courts. Smith also said that Assange encouraged sources to circumvent legal safeguards on information and build a pattern of “illegally procuring and providing” classified information to Wikileaks for distribution to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to the arguments of the US and the SSHD, Edward Fitzgerald KC countered the suggestion that the political offence exception to extradition, enshrined in the UK-US Extradition Treaty but not provided for in the latest domestic Extradition Act, was outmoded, or that Parliament had actively decided  to do away with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This country continues to sign treaties that provide that bar,” which also forms part of model extradition agreements produced by the UN and Interpol. The US is “seeking extradition on the basis of UK-US extradition Treaty”, which formed the basis of Julian Assange’s detention, so one “can’t escape the treaty.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Summers KC, for Julian Assange, told the court that the respondents had simply not answered the arguments put to them. It was “impressive” that the respondents had opined on the limits of responsible journalism for two hours without mentioning that the revelations at issue here were state crimes of the highest order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said it was not surprising that Clair Dobbin could not give a convincing answer on what should happen in a case where secret information had been solicited and published, and where redaction had taken place. The European Court of Human Rights in Strasbourg’s Article 10 case law required that a balancing of interests take place, even where classified or secret information was concerned. The precedent the US Government relied on was so old it pre-dated the UK Human Rights Act and the treatment of freedom of expression rights had moved on since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you think Strasbourg would consider the Article 10 argument,” he told the court, “then it must be arguable here.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At around 4.30, Dame Victoria Sharp told the court that the decision on permission to appeal would be reserved for a future date after 4 March 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://assangecourt.report/february-21-24-pm</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://assangecourt.report/february-21-24-pm</guid>
        
        
        <category>Reports</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Assange Court Report: February 21 - morning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assange not a journalist or entitled to protection, lawyers for US Government tell court&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proceedings resumed this morning with the court hearing legal submissions from the prosecution concerning why WikiLeaks Publisher Julian Assange should be denied permission to appeal his extradition. As with the first day of hearing, Mr Assange was not in court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clair Dobbin KC for the Crown Prosecution Service, arguing on behalf of the United States, opened by telling the court that Assange could not be considered a journalist and the affidavit submitted by the US addressed every aspect of the defence arguments. “The charges might be unprecedented but what he did was also unprecedented,” she said. 
After some minutes, Judge Sharp announced a pause of the proceedings because it was necessary to make sure that people in Court 3 could hear them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Dobbin, Mr Assange’s actions were different from a journalist’s in that he solicited the bulk disclosure of secret documents, was complicit to Ms. Manning’s theft of classified information and also responsible for ‘indiscriminately and knowingly’ publishing that information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WikiLeaks is ‘an organisation that advertises itself as soliciting illegally obtained material,’ the KC said; adding that the defence arguments related to Article 10, protecting freedom of speech, cannot be considered valid. The second superseding indictment laid against Mr Assange just before the extradition hearing in the District Court put a different complexion on his conduct, showing his communications with hackers and soliciting disclosures from security agencies.&lt;br /&gt;
The key point, she said, is not just the content of journalistic stories but rather in the methods journalists use to produce them. It’s about the “lawfulness of their conduct,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responding to another argument out forward by Assange’s legal team yesterday, Ms Dobbin went on to question whether Chelsea Manning could really be considered a whistleblower. “The sheer extent of the indiscriminate nature of the disclosures that Ms Manning made” of national defence material, in contravention of the duties she had as a member of the US military, would surely rule that out, she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One point that attracted the judges’ attention was the issue of what protections Julian Assange would have in the United States. One of the witness statements the US Government had provided to the District Court questioned whether Assange would be entitled to First Amendment protections should he find himself in an American courtroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an interjection a the end of the session, Mr Justice Johnson suggested that this was clearly relevant to the prohibition of discrimination included in the 2003 Extradition Act: “The test is not that he would be prejudiced, it is that he might be prejudiced on the grounds of his nationality”. He then asked if was possible to prove that a foreign national is entitled to the same rights as a US citizen. Dobbin could not identify any evidence that was relevant to this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case continues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://assangecourt.report/february-21-24-am</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://assangecourt.report/february-21-24-am</guid>
        
        
        <category>Reports</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Assange Day X Day 2 Hearing Photos: February 21, 2024</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Photos from the application for renewal hearing of Julian Assange at the Royal Courts of Justice in London, February 21, 2024. All photos credit: Guy Smallman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You are welcome to reproduce these photos for free as part of the contribution of this archive. Please include a tagline “credit: Guy Smallman”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;section class=&quot;recent-posts&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;row listrecent&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;

&lt;script&gt;

var gallery_images = [];
var gallery_captions = { 
};
var gallery_credits = {  
};
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;myModal&quot; class=&quot;modal&quot; onclick=&quot;closeModal()&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;gclose cursor&quot; onclick=&quot;closeModal()&quot;&gt;&amp;times;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;modal-content&quot; id=&quot;modal_content&quot; onclick=&quot;closeModal()&quot;&gt;
            &lt;img class=&quot;myimg item-fade&quot; onload=&quot;fadeIn()&quot; id=&quot;slideimg&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;numbertext&quot; id=&quot;number_div&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt; 
        &lt;div class=&quot;caption-container item-fade&quot; id=&quot;caption-container&quot; onclick=&quot;ignoreClick()&quot;&gt;
            &lt;p id=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;  
      
       
      &lt;!-- Next/previous controls --&gt;
      &lt;a class=&quot;gprev&quot; onclick=&quot;plusSlides(event,-1)&quot;&gt;&amp;#10094;&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;a class=&quot;gnext&quot; onclick=&quot;plusSlides(event,1)&quot;&gt;&amp;#10095;&lt;/a&gt;
  
      &lt;!-- Caption text --&gt;
      
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://assangecourt.report/dayx-photos-en/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://assangecourt.report/dayx-photos-en/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Photos</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Assange Court Report: February 20 - afternoon</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If extradited, Assange could face death penalty, court hears&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The press should be able to publish what it knows,’” Mark Summers KC said  at the outset of this afternoon’s court session, arguing that the original judge in the case had made a fundamental mistake by underrating the novelty and danger of the US prosecution of WikiLeaks Publisher Julian Assange.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prosecution of a journalist and publisher under the US Espionage Act, argued Summers, was so unexpected and unusual that it represented a breach of Article 7 of the European Convention of Human Rights, which protects individuals from arbitrary or unpredictable charges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The danger of the Assange prosecution, Summers went on to argue, to Article 10 (freedom of expression) rights is fundamental. He pointed out that the lower court judge had heard evidence from authoritative figures regarding the practice of obtaining and releasing classified information in the United States, nothing terribly unusual in journalistic terms, with no prosecution for such acts. Considering this, the prosecution of the WikiLeaks founder as a publisher “crosses new legal frontiers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summers then analysed the relevance of Article 10 of the European Convention of Human Rights in the case. Importantly, he noted that the case law of the European Court of Human Rights (ECtHR) in Strasbourg – to which this extradition case may be appealed in due course – regarding whistleblowers had evolved a great deal over the past decade and that UK law had not caught up with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He argued that, if the case of WikiLeaks source Chelsea Manning had come before it today, the Strasbourg court would likely have recognised her as a whistleblower, deserving of legal protections. Publishing leaked national security information would be legal because it is “protected by universally recognised principles of free speech,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running through some of the criteria the ECtHR has employed in important whistleblowing cases that have come before it in recent years, he argued that Chelsea Manning was ‘conscience driven’, and exposing state criminality is ‘at the highest level of public interest.’ If Chelsea Manning would be recognised as a whistleblower under current Article 10 case law, it should be clear that publication of those disclosures would also be protected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judge Dame Victoria Sharp interjected by asking if he had supporting case law  court for whistleblower protection instances where the names of government sources had been revealed, given the publication of unredacted cables in this case. Mark Summers KC responded that the ECtHR would likely make a context specific judgement on this and that it had been ‘a glaring legal error’ from the District Judge not to balance the risk of harming people with the public interest in disclosing information about tortures, extrajudicial imprisonments, and war crimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edward Fitzgerald KC then rose to present the final part of the appeal arguments, which focused on the ability of Julian Assange to receive a fair trial in the US.  Citing statements supplied to the lower court by Gordon Kromberg, a prosecutor in the Eastern District of Virginia, where Assange has been indicted, Fitzgerald said “the US government has argued that Julian would have no protection under the First Amendment of the US Constitution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judge Sharp interjected again to refer to the diplomatic assurances given by the US Government to the effect that Assange might eventually be able to be transferred to Australia to serve any sentence. Fitzgerald reminded her that, for that to happen, there is a requirement of “remaining on pre-trial remand”, and Assange would have had to have exhausted all his possible appeals, even if Australia were happy to receive him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attention then turned to issues that, Mr Assange’s legal team argued, the UK Home Secretary had not taken into account in her decision to allow the extradition to go ahead. These included the potential for additional charges to be laid on Mr Assange once he arrived in the US and the possibility that Mr Assange may be ‘subject to a death penalty’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Summers referred to the fact that Chelsea Manning had been charged – though not convicted on a treason charge (“Aiding the Enemy”) and explained that, consequently, Assange could conceivably be charged with aiding treasonous acts, a charge that would carry the death penalty. As such “extradition which exposes a defendant to the death penalty is prohibited in all circumstances by section 94 of the UK-US extradition treaty.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Justice Johnson then asked if the death penalty issue could be addressed by the existing diplomatic assurance. Summers KC denied this was the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second day of the hearing will focus on the response to these arguments from the Government of the United States and the UK Home Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case continues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://assangecourt.report/february-20-24-pm</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://assangecourt.report/february-20-24-pm</guid>
        
        
        <category>Reports</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Assange Court Report: February 20 - morning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Espionage Act charges are “quintessentially political,” Assange defence argues&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of protesters showing support to Julian Assange assembled this morning outside London’s Royal Courts of Justice, for what could be the WikiLeaks publisher’s final opportunity to put his arguments against extradition in a UK courtroom. Assange is facing an unprecedented US prosecution under the 1917 Espionage Act centering on WikiLeaks’ publications in 2010-2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week’s two-day hearing is taking place to request permission for an appeal against points rejected at Westminster Magistrates Court in January 2021 as well as the  extradition order signed in June 2022 by former UK Home Secretary Priti Patel.  These matters, set to one side at a relatively early stage in these extradition proceedings, include some of the most critical issues raised by the US prosecution, including whether the US prosecution is politically motivated and the likely impact on media freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assange was reported to be ill and unable to attend in person or via video link today’s hearing, where his legal team are asking two High Court judges – Dame Victoria Sharp and the Hon Mr Justice Jeremy Johnson KC – to grant a new appeal hearing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barrister Edward Fitzgerald KC focused on the argument that extradition would be politically motivated and supplied examples of cases related to espionage where extraditions were denied because the charges associated to it were assessed to be Espionage, he told the Court, is “quintessentially a political offence” and extradition on these grounds is prohiited under   Article 4(1) of the UK-US Extradition Treaty of 2003. Granting extradition in these circumstances would be “an abuse of process”, he said. “It’s a big step to say this centuries old protection, incorporated in every UK-US extradition treaty, has been superseded, silently”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fitzgerald highlighted statements made by US politicans and government officals, arguing that these demonstrate Suggesting that the extradition is politically motivated, reminding the court that “Mike Pompeo defined WikiLeaks as a hostile, non-state intelligence agency.” He suggested the District Judge could not reasonably have concluded that describing Wikileaks in such way had no particular relevance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Summers KC, another member of Assange’s defence team, then made the argument that the WikiLeaks disclosures exposed state-level criminality, itself a political act. There was no question that the publications had revealed crimes of the highest level of importance and that they had, in some respects, produced changes in the situations concerned. Evidence provided to the District Court by figures like Daniel Ellsberg and Noam Chomsky amply showed that Mr Assange had a distinct political philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to explain that this position was one that the Government of the United States was hostile to, refering to documented interference in attempts to secure accountability for torture initiated by other countries, including Poland and Spain, and opposition to investigations by the International Criminal Court in the Hague. This, he argued, helped account for the  “substantial malevolence” behind the prosecution, which could only be understood as a form of retaliation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, said Summers, reached extraordinary lengths, with attacks on Assange dicussed at the highest level of the US Government. 
“Donald Trump himself requested to be provided with options on how to do it”, he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The court rose for lunch at 2 PM in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case continues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://assangecourt.report/february-20-24</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://assangecourt.report/february-20-24</guid>
        
        
        <category>Reports</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
